## WILLIAM M. MAINTZ II

5 Lussac Court Lake St. Louis, MO 63367 bill@maintz.com

H: (636) 625-1118 C: (314) 852-6074

#### **CAREER SUMMARY**

Senior-level Hands-On Technical Lead / Solution Architect / Software Developer with an extensive background in application development and/or modification. Possesses a well-rounded developer background in the conception, design, development, and implementation of a full array of computer products and systems. A versatile communicator who has demonstrated excellent oral and written communication skills by delivering technical and business information to diverse audiences, from small senior management groups to large convention assemblies. Recognized for his ability to bridge the technical and business aspects of the organization as the technology changes and impacts core business values. And most importantly, a problem solver with the knowledge and experience to quickly solve problems and keep application development moving forward.

#### **KEY COMPETENCIES**

Business Requirements Gathering Technical Specification Documentation Testing/Quality Assurance/Control Operational Analysis Change Management Guidance/Mentoring Systems and Procedures Development Custom Software Development Personnel and Staff Development

#### SELECTED ACHIEVEMENTS

### Developed and implemented a code generation system and supporting infrastructure

As the architect and designer of TriZetto's Launchware, I developed a set of scripts and utilities designed to streamline the code promotion process and developed a code generation system as well as the supporting file and utility subsystems which removed the manual localization of files and automated the creation of over 1500 report generation scripts on two separate operating systems and multiple servers for each client at TriZetto's hosting center in Denver, CO. Result: The error rates associated with the promotion and implementation of those programs and scripts was reduced from 28% to 2%.

## Quickly developed websites

Using static HTML, dynamic ASP.NET master pages, JSP/Java, Razor C#, and most recently, AngularJS, Bootstrap, node.js and Responsive Web Design using HTML5 and CSS3, I developed websites using each of those technologies/frameworks and have developed expertise on the complimentary tools used with each, like npm, bower, grunt, and gulp. This experience includes the use of multiple editors, IDEs, repositories, SQL back-ends, graphic design tools, compilers, syntax checkers, and automated testing tools.

# Reduced Change Management efforts through reusable code and customization through CSS

While working as the Lead Developer of a firm's multi-client Java, JSP, and WebSphere-based web portal utilizing XML SOAP web services to acquire and update sensitive PHI data, I developed client-specific front-ends (the GUI) using cascading style sheets and HTML, custom back-end code for each client's web portal and web services, providing unique graphics, color scheme, and functionality to each, while maintaining the same reusable base core system. This approach reduced the testing effort as well as the source code and change management processes which were maintained within a TFS platform.

#### Extracted and converted XML error logs into meaningful and readable reports

While working as the Technical Lead on a national firm's software upgrade project, I designed and developed a process that would read the XML-based error logs generated from daily batch processes and generate meaningful and human-readable reports with a standard output so that the operational results of the old version of the application being upgraded could be compared with the new version of the application. The standardized output of each was further analyzed so that any differences in the two systems could be quickly identified. This tool saved hundreds of hours in test analysis and triage.

### Converted concepts to program designs and created project plans for their development

While working as the Data Architect of an international firm's computer software subsidiary, I analyzed the research data and then, using the ERwin data-modeling tool, created the data model for a multi-lingual, relational database for an internationally distributed software product. The design allowed each software program in the multi-program suite to run independently of one another or in conjunction with any one or all of the other programs and have its contents presented in English or one of seven foreign languages.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### All Business Computer Services LLC, Lake St. Louis, MO -- Senior Consultant 2005 – Present

Working as a Senior Technical Consultant and Developer, helped several clients design and develop new systems to either replace old ones or that would address a new business need. This included several major Healthcare Management Organizations like BCBS of Michigan, BCBS of Louisiana, BS of California, BCBS of Western New York, United Healthcare, APS Healthcare, OSF Healthcare, MED3000, and Fidelis Care Because of a diverse technical background, the skill set provided to these and other organizations included requirements gathering, solution design, infrastructure architecting, software and SQL development, environment management, code promotion automation, automated QA testing, production deployment, and post-production support - essentially all phases of the full SDLC model. The excellence in technical leadership and superior consultation has resulted in several profound letters of recommendation.

## Beacon Hill Technologies, Chicago, IL – Senior App Dev Project Manager

2014-2015

As the Senior Project Manager for three major projects within Express Scripts, Inc., worked with multiple onshore and offshore teams in multiple locations to define, design, develop, and test the solutions to identified business requirements prior to implementing them into the production environment. This included working within the EPMO department of ESI to coordinate the use of matrixed resources who were also working on several other projects. Simultaneously managed multiple projects, each having separate delivery dates (one having six separate staggered implementations) and successfully deployed each project's solution into production under budget.

### GenPact/Jawood, Bingham Farms, MI – Senior App Dev Project Manager

2013-2014

As the Senior Project Manager for a major project within Noridian Healthcare Solutions, was responsible for coordinating the replacement of their EDI Front-End application. This included project management, infrastructure design, environment management, training coordination and scheduling, and executive-level reporting. The new solution utilized a more robust and scalable system architecture which necessitated the deployment of a newly architected infrastructure into each of four environments defined within their SDLC model and the coordination of efforts and collaboration with a 3<sup>rd</sup> party software firm. Technical leadership was required to identify the many connection points within the process flow so that the implementation would allow the smooth transition from the old system to the new. Additionally, I took over the project management of a Provider Portal Project which used an Agile development methodology and the Jira tool to manage, track, and report on its progress.

#### Lanier & Associates, Atlanta, GA -- Senior Consultant - Technical Lead

2003 - 2005

Technical Lead at TriZetto's Denver Hosting Center - multiple projects. In the first of four projects, led the development of a suite of PERL programs that merged the contents of two FACETS RDBMS databases into one, maintaining full referential integrity in the process. In a second project, led the development of a an automated EC Gateway Script Duplication sub-system that reduced the development time of HIPAA Gateway Scripts from 5 days to 5 hours. In a third project, automated the creation of UNIX Korn shell scripts that created reports and transmitted them via ftp to a remote client site, again allowing TriZetto to realize the benefit of significantly reduced development time. In the fourth project, automated the conversion of raw data into fully relational data that allowed it to be quickly inserted into a FACETS database, thereby saving hundreds of hours that would have been spent performing the same task manually.

### Partec, Inc., St. Louis, MO -- Senior Consultant

2000 - 2002

Worked on numerous projects within multiple companies. As the Chief Technology Officer for CoForce.com, managed a cross-functional group and led the reorganization of the software development team by implementing standard full life cycle development processes, including complete change management, system and user testing, Quality Assurance, and code migration procedures. As the Project Manager and Database Architect of the OnTrack 2000 Project for Computer Sales International, developed a complete project plan for the development of an n-tier, web-based application that included the training, development, rollout, and support of that product. Also helped manage the eight in-house and four vendor team members. As the UNIX Technical Lead and Object Developer for Blue Cross Blue Shield of Missouri, simultaneously led the technical effort on two project teams and contributed to a third, created a common code library, managed a team of five Unix Developers, and coordinated seven additional developers to standardize the error reporting and program log reporting systems. Helped lead a cross-functional team of five to develop a Windows-based Intranet and Internet application for distributing files to external resources.

#### **EDUCATION**

- M.S. Full-Cycle Computer Software Development, School of Hard Knocks©, St. Louis, MO
- B.S. Business Administration/Management Information Systems, Southern Illinois University

## **TECHNICAL EXPERTISE**

#### **OPERATING SYSTEMS:**

Windows NT / 95 / 98 / 2000 / 2003 / 2008 / 2012 / XP / Vista / 7 / 8 / 10, UNIX, AIX, HP/UX, LINUX

## LANGUAGES/FRAMEWORKS:

C, C++, C#, Visual Basic, VBA, VB Script, Java, JavaScript, JSP, JSON, JQuery, Windows Script, PowerShell, UNIX Shell Script (sh, ksh, csh), PERL, HTML/HTML5, Razor CSHTML, CSS/CSS3, ASP.NET, ADO.NET, MVC, XSLT, XML, XAML, Silverlight (3-5), Entity Framework, Angular.js, Bootstrap.js, node.js

#### **DATABASES:**

• Sybase (11.x, 12.x, 15.x), Oracle (7.x, 8i, 9, 11), MS SQL Server (6.5, 7.0, 2005, 2008, 2010, 2012), Informix, DB2/2, ERwin DB Modeling (3.5.2), Power Designer 10.0

#### Tools:

MS Office (2003-2013), MS Project, MS Visio, SharePoint, TFS, Visual Studio (6-2013), Expression Blend (3-4), TFS, SourceSafe, PVCS, sccs, git, Jira, Apache Ant, npm, grunt, gulp, bower, yeoman, Karma, Protractor, Eclipse, WebSphere, MS IE, Netscape Navigator, Google Chrome, Firefox, EC Gateway, SSIS, SSMS, SSRS, Crystal Reports, Business Objects, Data Integrator, Brio, HPXR, Clarity

#### **OTHER DISCIPLINES:**

• EDI, X12, ETL, Data Mart, Data Warehouse, n-tier App Dev, TriZetto/Erisco FACETS versions 2.94-5.01, Broadband RF, Bar Code Labeling